<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-20T16:48:35+00:00</updated><id>https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/feed.xml</id><title type="html">McNutt Lab Website</title><subtitle>Explore the innovative research of a distinguished scientist and educator dedicated to unraveling the mysteries of toxicity and regeneration. Delve into cutting-edge studies ranging from molecular mechanisms to multi-organ responses, aimed at developing transformative therapies for human diseases. Join us in advancing scientific frontiers, fostering creativity, excellence, and mentorship for the scientists of tomorrow.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">New Research Shows Drug Used to Treat Neuromuscular Weakness Could Counter Botulism</title><link href="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2022/08/01/WakeNeuromuscular.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Research Shows Drug Used to Treat Neuromuscular Weakness Could Counter Botulism" /><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T16:47:23+00:00</updated><id>https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2022/08/01/WakeNeuromuscular</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2022/08/01/WakeNeuromuscular.html"><![CDATA[<p>Wake Forest Institute for Regenerative Medicine (WFIRM) researchers are investigating a drug used to treat neuromuscular weakness as a potential treatment for botulism, a rare but serious disease.</p>

<p>Botulinum neurotoxins (BoNTs) are a family of bacterial poisons – the most poisonous substances known – responsible for the clinical disease known as botulism. These neurotoxins act within nerve terminals to destroy proteins necessary for muscle contraction, causing paralysis that develops into respiratory arrest and can lead to death. The Centers for Disease Control (CDC) considers botulinum neurotoxins a Tier 1 agent, posing the highest risk following accidental or deliberate misuse.</p>

<p>The deliberate misuse aspect of the toxin is what drives the WFIRM researchers and their work to find a treatment. Currently, the only specific treatment for botulism is early administration with antitoxin. However, antitoxin is only effective if administered before prior botulism symptoms are evident. Once symptoms emerge, three out of four patients require long-term artificial ventilation for survival.</p>

<p>“Despite decades of effort, there are no antidotes for the life-threatening consequences of botulism. This failure is primarily because the toxin hides within the nerve terminal, where it poses a challenging target for delivery of therapeutic molecules,” said corresponding author of the paper Patrick McNutt, PhD, who leads this research effort at WFIRM.</p>

<p>The researchers build on their previous work to show that administration of the FDA-approved drug 3,4-diaminopyridine (3,4-DAP) reverses botulism symptoms in a pre-clinical model. The drug is an approved treatment for Lambert Eaton Myasthenic Syndrome, an autoimmune disease caused by reduced acetylcholine release and neuromuscular weakness. Botulism paralysis is caused by reduction of acetylcholine release from motor nerve terminals to subthreshold levels required for muscle contraction.</p>

<p>Acetylcholine is the chief chemical messenger of the parasympathetic nervous system, the part of the autonomic nervous system that contracts smooth muscles, dilates blood vessels, and slows heart rate.</p>

<p>For this study, recently published in Molecular Medicine, the researchers developed a continuous 3,4-DAP infusion model and measured dose-dependent effects on toxic signs and survival after a lethal dose of botulinum neurotoxin. They found that continuous infusion with the drug produces rapid and sustained therapeutic benefits while survival requires continuous infusion for longer than four days.</p>

<p>“This is the first small-molecule therapy to directly reverse toxic signs and promote survival when administered post-symptomatically after a lethal dose of botulism,” said McNutt. “Our data supports the immediate clinical use of DAP in botulism patients.”</p>

<p><a href="https://school.wakehealth.edu/research/institutes-and-centers/wake-forest-institute-for-regenerative-medicine/awards-honors-and-media-coverage/2022/new-research-shows-drug-used-to-treat-neuromuscular-weakness-could-counter-botulism">Original post</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Wake Forest University School of Medicine</name></author><category term="biology" /><category term="medicine" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Wake Forest Institute for Regenerative Medicine (WFIRM) researchers are investigating a drug used to treat neuromuscular weakness as a potential treatment for botulism, a rare but serious disease.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/wake.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/wake.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Trojan Horse Antidotes Designed to Neutralize Lethal Botulinum Toxin</title><link href="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2021/01/11/TrojanHorse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trojan Horse Antidotes Designed to Neutralize Lethal Botulinum Toxin" /><published>2021-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T16:47:23+00:00</updated><id>https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2021/01/11/TrojanHorse</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2021/01/11/TrojanHorse.html"><![CDATA[<p>Two research groups have designed chimeric fusion proteins that constitute a new “trojan horse” approach to neutralize lethal botulinum toxins.</p>

<p>Botulinum neurotoxins (BoNTs)—a family of bacterial toxins with seven major serotypes (BoNT/A to BoNT/G)—are classified by the United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) as one of the most dangerous bioterrorism agents. BoNTs infiltrate into motor neurons, block neurotransmitter release, and stop essential functions such as breathing.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.genengnews.com/topics/drug-discovery/trojan-horse-antidotes-designed-to-neutralize-lethal-botulinum-toxin/">Original post</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Genetic Engineering &amp; Biotechnology News</name></author><category term="biology" /><category term="medicine" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Two research groups have designed chimeric fusion proteins that constitute a new “trojan horse” approach to neutralize lethal botulinum toxins.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/lead-image-e1681832925603.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/lead-image-e1681832925603.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New strategy to fight botulinum toxin - expert available</title><link href="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2021/01/06/BotToxEurekA.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New strategy to fight botulinum toxin - expert available" /><published>2021-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T16:47:23+00:00</updated><id>https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2021/01/06/BotToxEurekA</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2021/01/06/BotToxEurekA.html"><![CDATA[<p>Related to new research published in the January issue of Science Translational Medicine, Patrick McNutt, PhD, of the Wake Forest Institute for Regenerative Medicine, was part of the research team that demonstrated a new “Trojan horse” approach that produces strong antidotal efficacy in treating lethal botulism in mice, guinea pigs and rhesus macaque monkeys.</p>

<p>Furthermore, in a companion article, an independent team demonstrated that a related drug has robust efficacy in mice.</p>

<p>“This is one of those serendipitous moments in science where two groups, working independently, demonstrate similar results for a long-standing problem,” McNutt said. “We are currently modifying this drug to enhance its therapeutic properties against botulism and exploring whether the same approach can be repurposed to treat other neuronal diseases.”</p>

<p>In 2010, Konstantin Ichtchenko (New York University School of Medicine) conceived of a novel ‘trojan horse’ strategy to treat botulism. This strategy is based on using a non-toxic form of BoNT to deliver therapeutic antibodies to paralyzed neurons, blocking wild-type toxin activity and accelerating recovery from paralysis. Over the past decade, Konstantin established collaborations with Patrick McNutt (Wake Forest Institute of Regenerative Medicine), Phil Band (Cytodel, Inc.) and Chuck Shoemaker (Tufts University) to develop and test this new drug in a variety of experimental models.</p>

<p>Botulinum neurotoxins (BoNTs) are a family of bacterial poisons responsible for the clinical disease known as botulism. BoNT acts within nerve terminals to destroy proteins necessary for evoking muscle contraction, causing muscle paralysis that develops into respiratory arrest at lethal concentrations. BoNT is the most poisonous substances known, with median lethal doses that are over a million-fold lower than cyanide.</p>

<p>Because of its extraordinary potency and long duration of action, the toxin is considered a Tier 1 agent by the CDC, which is reserved for the most dangerous public threats. These same properties render BoNT a highly effective cosmetic and therapeutic drug (e.g., BOTOX) with diverse clinical indications. Despite decades of effort, there are no antidotes for the life-threatening consequences of botulism. This failure is primarily because the toxin hides within the nerve terminal, where it poses a challenging target for delivery of therapeutic molecules.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/664935">Original post</a></p>]]></content><author><name>EurekAlert!</name></author><category term="biology" /><category term="medicine" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Related to new research published in the January issue of Science Translational Medicine, Patrick McNutt, PhD, of the Wake Forest Institute for Regenerative Medicine, was part of the research team that demonstrated a new “Trojan horse” approach that produces strong antidotal efficacy in treating lethal botulism in mice, guinea pigs and rhesus macaque monkeys.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/800px-Botulinum_toxin_3BTA.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/800px-Botulinum_toxin_3BTA.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Patrick McNutt Talks Chemical Weapons</title><link href="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2015/04/20/BioChemWeapons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patrick McNutt Talks Chemical Weapons" /><published>2015-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T16:47:23+00:00</updated><id>https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2015/04/20/BioChemWeapons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/2015/04/20/BioChemWeapons.html"><![CDATA[<p>Army scientist discusses medical research being carried out to understand and protect against warfare agents</p>

<p>Just four days after defending a Ph.D. in molecular biology at Princeton University, Patrick McNutt started basic infantry training at Fort Benning, Ga. “That led to some culture shock,” he recalls with a chuckle. But the experience prepared him to deploy in 2005–06 to Iraq, where he provided science and technology ground support as a member of the Reserve Officers’ Training Corps, a military program that financially supported the bachelor’s degree he received from Wake Forest University.</p>

<p>Today, McNutt, who clearly doesn’t relish a humdrum life, works for the U.S. Army Medical Research Institute of Chemical Defense (USAMRICD), the primary laboratory of the Department of Defense for investigating medical aspects of chemical weapons defense. He studies the biological and biochemical mechanisms of nerve agents, mustard gas, and botulinum neurotoxins. What follows is a recent discussion (edited for length and clarity) he had with C&amp;EN about why chemical weapons defense research is relevant today.</p>

<p><a href="https://cen.acs.org/articles/93/i16/Patrick-McNutt-Talks-Chemical-Weapons.html">Original post</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Biological Chemistry</name></author><category term="biology" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="botulism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Army scientist discusses medical research being carried out to understand and protect against warfare agents]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/09316-scitech2-McNutt.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://calebaguayo.github.io/McNuttLab/images/Posts/09316-scitech2-McNutt.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>